Artifact Collection AC
Tufts Archival Research Center
Artifact Collection
circa 2150 BCE -- 2007 CE
Tufts Archival Research Center
Digital Collections and Archives
AC
27.2 Linear Feet
215 Artifact(s)
2 Digital Object(s)
The Artifact Collection is an artificial collection created in 2001, which consists of materials relating to Tufts University and people associated with Tufts University; artifacts from ancient cultures and modern; and manuscripts, prints, and other texts, all dating circa 2150 BCE – 2007 CE. Materials included in this collection are coins; cuneiform tablets and cones; illuminated manuscripts; leaves from early printed books; maps; paintings; prints; sculptures; textiles; and other artifacts.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into six series: Tufts materials; Coins; Cuneiform, scarabs, memorial slab, and tomb figure; Manuscript, printed, and book history materials; Portraits, paintings, and sculptures; and other artifacts.
Scope and Contents
The artifact collection is an artificial collection created in 2001, which consists of materials relating to Tufts University and people associated with Tufts University; artifacts from ancient cultures and modern; and manuscripts, prints, and other texts, all dating circa 2150 BCE – 2007 CE. Material relating to Tufts University includes plaques, trophies, and medals; jewelry; textiles; papers and printed materials; and other objects belonging or relating to Tuft University and people associated with Tufts University. Artifacts from ancient cultures include examples of papyrus, cuneiform, scarabs, memorial slabs, a tomb figure, and coins representing varied cultures such as Egypt, Sumer, the Akkadian Empire, and Greece. There are also examples of coins from modern cultures. Artifacts in this collection include sculptures, a bamboo flute, and a cannon ball. Texts and printed materials include autographs and correspondence; illuminated and early manuscripts; leaves from early printed books, some with woodblock illustrations; governmental documents; maps; painting and prints; Illuminated and early manuscript leaves and leaves from early printed books are mainly from educational or religious texts and are in various languages, including English, Hebrew, Latin, German, Italian, French and Flemish.
Biographical / Historical
Tufts Archival Research Center is the Tufts University steward for all archival records and materials of significant and historical relevance to the college.
The collection began as the University Archives, which were incorporated in 1965 by the Tufts University Board of Trustees (Annual Reports 1965-1988). Previously, the position of archivist was loosely created in 1959 as a means of processing and acquiring important university and student records for preservation. This role was filled by Tufts history professor and historian Russell L. Miller, who also wrote the Tufts University history "Light on the Hill." The archives were considered a department of the University Library (known as Eaton and then Wessell at that time), overseen by the College of Arts, Sciences and Engineering.
The university's archives were first kept in Eaton Library, but moved to the Wessell Library building in 1965. Originals of some records were sent to vaults in Ballou Hall for storage. In 1991, due to budget issues, the university archivist was laid off. When the office was reopened in 1997, it was as the University Archives and Special Collections, also located as a department within the Tisch Library.
In July 2001, Digital Collections and Archives (DCA) was created when the University Archives was tasked with developing a Tufts Digital Library. The department moved from the College of Arts, Science and Engineering to the Central Administration, directed by the University Provost. The Special Collections department remained under Tisch Library.
In January 2023, DCA was renamed Tufts Archival Research Center (TARC) to better reflect the mission and services offered by the department.
TARC is currently physically housed in the Tisch Library building.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Cuneiform; Coins (money); Artifacts (object genre); Textiles; University history; Maps (documents); Busts (sculpture)
- Tufts materials, circa 1700 -- 2007; AC.001.000002
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains artifacts and printed materials dated circa 1700 -- 2007 that are associated with Tufts University in general and as well as with people associated with Tufts University. Artifacts include jewelry such as pins and watches; plaques, trophies, and medal; textiles such as Tufts apparel and clothing belonging to the Tufts family; materials gathered from Alonzo Ames miner's birthplace; and other objects such as elephant figurines and copper engraving plates for Tufts diplomas and certificates.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged into 6 sub-series: Alonzo Ames Miner materials; Jewelry; Other objects; Papers and printed materials; Plaques, trophies, and medals; and Textiles.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research.
  - Alonzo Ames Miner materials, circa 1700 -- 1927; AC.000237
    This sub-series contains materials gathered from the birthplace of Alonzo Ames Miner, Tufts's second president (1862 – 1875), as well as stamped envelopes addressed to him and a silver spoon engraved with his name, circa 1700 – 1927.
    No order has been imposed on this sub-series.
    This sub-series is open for research.
    - Section of clapboard from the birthplace of Alonzo Ames Miner in East Lempster, NH, undated; AC.006.00001 (Box 6)
      Open for research.
    - Stamped envelopes addressed to Alonzo Miner, circa 1877 -- 1927; AC.011.00022 (Box 11)
    - Hand hewn nails from the birthplace of Alonzo Ames Miner in East Lempster, NH, circa 1700-1899; AC.047.00010 (Box Shared 16)
    - Silver spoon with Alonzo Ames Miner inscription, circa 1850 - 1894; AC.047.00015 (Box Shared 16)
      Tray 2
    - Piece of granite rock foundation from birthplace of Alonzo Ames Miner in East Lempster, NH, undated; AC.047.00017 (Box Shared 16)
      Tray 3
  - Jewelry, circa 1818 -- 1968; AC.000236
    This sub-series contains jewelry, including class, fraternity, and Tufts pins; a medallion; World War I Liberty Loan and Victory buttons; and watches dating circa 1818 – 1968.
    - Class pins, 1929; AC.017.00002 (Box Shared 9)
      Bottom tray. Resembles a luggage tag.
    - Silver pocket watch with chain and pendant belonging to Charles Tufts, 1818; AC.017.00003 (Box Shared 9)
      Bottom tray. Gift of Sumner Robinson.
    - "Order of the Coffee Pot," medallion, belonging to Henry W. Cory, 1867; AC.017.00012 (Box Shared 9)
      Middle tray.
      Cory, Henry William; Order of the Coffee Pot
    - Tufts Weekly pin, circa 1895 -- 1968; AC.047.00001 (Box Shared 16)
      Tray 1
    - Tuftonian pin, 1928; AC.047.00002 (Box Shared 16)
    - Tufts pin, 1899; AC.047.00004 (Box Shared 16)
    - Tufts pin, undated; AC.047.00005 (Box Shared 16)
    - Zeta Psi fraternity pin belonging to Theodore Messer, 1918; AC.047.00006 (Box Shared 16)
    - Five Liberty Loan and Victory buttons from WWI, 1917; AC.047.00007 (Box Shared 16)
    - Gold Hodgson, Kennard & Co wristwatch belonging to Morton Prince, circa 1889 -- 1929; AC.017.00001 (Box Shared 9)
      Morton Prince was a professor of nervous diseases at Tufts from 1902 until 1912, when he was appointed professor emeritus and awarded an honorary degree. (Taken from Henry H. Banks' "A Century of Excellence: The History of Tufts University School of Medicine 1893 –1993 p107-108).
      Prince, Morton
  - Other objects, circa 1815 -- 1979; AC.000233
    This sub-series is arranged in alphabetical order.
    This sub-series contains objects relating to both Tufts University and people associated with Tufts University dating circa 1815 – 1979. These objects include elephant figurines, engraving plates, and commemorative objects.
    - Antique frame double frame [Empty], undated; AC.047.00019 (Box Shared 16)
    - Antique single frame [Empty], undated; AC.047.00018 (Box Shared 16)
    - Bookmark: Upon the occasion of the breaking of ground for Tufts University Library, 1962-06-09; AC.047.00016 (Box Shared 16)
    - Cane belonging to Hosea Ballou II, circa 1815 -- 1861; AC.038.00001 (Box Shared 11)
      In artifact box along with animal prod from MS 002/001-012.
    - Cigarette case, 1929; AC.017.00007 (Box Shared 9)
      Middle tray. Tag on inside reads, "Gentleman's Favor at Senior Prom, Class of 1929. Henry S. Condon, 72 Ravine Road, Medford, Mass. 01255"
    - Copper engraving plates for Tufts diplomas and certificates, circa 1856 -- 1950; AC.019 (Box 19)
    - Elephant figurines, undated; AC.004.000001 (Box 4)
    - Fairbanks scale, circa 1800s; AC.017.00018 (Box Shared 10)
    - Hullabaloo, 1892 class horn, "Class Yell," 1892, AC.048 (Box 48)
    - James W. Tufts Company silver plated dish with cherry stamp, circa 1896 -- 1900; AC.039.00002 (Box 39)
    - Spoon commemorating the groundbreaking of Wessell Library, 1957-04-01; AC.047.00014 (Box Shared 16)
    - Miniature portrait of Thomas Goddard, circa 1830; AC.047.00009 (Box Shared 16)
      Goddard, Thomas A.
    - Tufts football, signed by team, 1979; AC.002.000001 (Box 2)
  - Papers and printed materials, circa 1767 -- 1969; AC.000232
    This sub-series contains papers and printed materials related to Tufts University and people associated with Tufts University dating circa 1767 – 1969. This includes matriculation books; the original deed for the land Tufts on which Tufts stands; maps and building plans; a codicil to the will of Rebeccah Davidson; and other Tufts printed documentation. More maps can be found in Series 4, Sub-series 7: Maps.
    This sub-series has is arranged in alphabetical order.
    - Architectural plans and drawings for a the Medical Education Building, Tufts University School of Medicine, 1969; AC.034.00001 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 6)
    - Codicil to will of Rebeccah Davidson, 1769-12-27; AC.011.00023 (Box 11)
    - Copies of Tufts College Library donation certificates, circa 1880; AC.041.00010 (Box 41)
    - Jackson College seal, undated; AC.041.00018 (Box 41)
    - Maps, circa 1852 -- 1947; AC.032.00002 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 8)
      Inventory is as follows: Map of Summerville, MA, circa 1852. Map of the Grounds of Tufts College, circa 1899. "Plan of Land belonging to Tufts College in Medford & Summerville", circa 1856. "A Map of the Ground of Tufts College" circa 1928. "Plan of Land in Medford & Somerville on the Westerly Slope of Winter Hill", circa 1875 – 1890 (date based on name of train station map). "Plan No. 5 of Land in Medford owned by William Tufts and others", circa 1861. "Plan No. 6, Land in Medford Owned by George F. Tufts", circa 1861-1900. "Plan No. 3. of Land in Medford belonging to Wm Tufts & others", circa 1854. "A Map of the Grounds of Tufts College", circa 1928. "Tufts College in Medford and Boston Mass", map, circa 1947.
    - Matriculation book, 1854 -- 1869; AC.037.00001 (Box 37)
    - Matriculation book, 1854 -- 1875; AC.036.00001 (Box 36)
      The matriculation book covers the years 1854-1875.
    - Original deed of the site of Tufts Universalist College, Boston, Mass., 1800; AC.011.00012 (Box 11)
    - Original petition of students for change in physical training charges, as passed at Trustees meeting, 1911-05-11; AC.047.00013 (Box Shared 16)
    - Preliminary master plan, map of Tufts University, 1957; AC.033.00001 (Box Large Map Case 3 Drawer 8)
  - Plaques, trophies, and medals, circa 1893 -- 1973; AC.000235
    This sub-series contains plaques, trophies, and medals presented to Tufts University and members of its community dating 1893 – 1973. These include sports trophies and plaques; debate trophies; and medals presented to Tufts alumni Vannevar Bush (1890 – 1974) and John T. Blake (1901 – 1987) for their achievements in the sciences and engineering.
    - Trophy in Annual Debating Contests between the Capen and the Knowlton Clubs, 1910; AC.001.000001 (Box 1)
      Gift of William Wallace McClench A1875
    - Student plaques and trophies, 1935 -- 1972; AC.003.000001
      - Intramural Tennis Championship, 1935 -- 1941; AC.003.00001 (Box 43)
      - Intramural Basketball Championship, 1936 -- 1942; AC.003.00002 (Box 43)
      - Tufts College Annual Christmas Sing, 1952 -- 1958; AC.003.00003 (Box 43)
      - Brown University Debate Tournament, Semifinalist, 1972; AC.003.00004 (Box 43)
      - Oswego Semi-Finals, 1970; AC.003.00005 (Box 43)
      - King's College Debate Tournament Octo-Finalist, 1972; AC.003.00006 (Box 43)
    - Plaque - Tufts College Annual Spring Sing, 1947 -- 1959; AC.013 (Box 13)
    - InterDormitory awards, 1959 -- 1960; AC.015 (Box 15)
    - Medallion from the Columbian Exposition presented to Tufts College, 1893; AC.017.00010 (Box Shared 9)
      Middle tray. Gift of Peter Noel Knost, A1958, C1961, H1968. Columbian Exposition was held in Chicago, 1893.
    - ESSC Forensic Tournament original oration fifth place trophy, 1971; AC.039.00003 (Box 39)
      Bottom tray.
    - University of Florida Gator Invitational Tournament trophy/cup, 1973; AC.039.00004 (Box 39)
    - Roosevelt Memorial Associations Medal of Honor presented to Vannevar Bush, 1945; AC.039.00005 (Box 39)
      Bush, Vannevar
    - Hamilton Tournament Columbia 1972, 2nd Place, AC.043.00001 (Box 43)
    - 3rd Place Overall Four Man Team S.N.E.I.D.T., 1971; AC.043.00002 (Box 43)
    - CFA Fall 1970 Varsity Debate 1st Place trophy, AC.044 (Box 44)
    - Purple Heart belonging to Donald A. Cowdery, F1946, circa 1942 -- 1946; AC.047.00008 (Box Shared 16)
    - Lemme Medal presented to Vannevar Bush by the American Institute of Electrical Engineers, 1935; AC.047.00011 (Box Shared 16)
    - Holley Medal presented to Vannevar Bush by the American Society of Mechanical Engineers, 1943; AC.047.00012
    - Vannevar Bush and John T. Blake medals and commemorative coins, circa 1901 -- 1969; AC.009 (Box 9)
      This box contains 10 medals presented to Vannevar Bush from 1924 -- 1969, 1 medal presented to John T. Blake in 1953, and 8 commemorative coins from circa 1901 -- 1965.
      Bush, Vannevar; Blake, John T.
    - Tufts Field Day medal, 1891; AC.000240; 0.1 Linear Feet (Box Shared 12)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Gift of Clover Nally, 2022, accession UA-2022-049.
      Medal for "First Prize Throwing Baseball."
  - Textiles, circa 1782 -- 2007; AC.000234
    This sub-series contains textiles related to the Tufts University and people associated with Tufts University dating circa 1782 – 1970. These include clothing belonging to the Tufts family; clothing worn by Tufts students and alumni; and banners made for Tufts classes.
    - Shirt belonging to Peter Tufts, 1782; AC.005.000001 (Box 5)
    - Sampler made by Hannah Tufts, circa 1800s; AC.011.00010 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence and documentation pertaining to Hannah Tufts' shawl, circa 1945 -- 1985; AC.016.00001 (Box 16)
      This folder contains donation information related to Hannah Tufts' shawl.
    - Shawl belonging to Hannah Tufts, circa 18th century; AC.016.00002 (Box 16)
    - Clothes and textiles, circa 1900 -- 2007; AC.021
      Items in box are not numbered, but #1 is at the bottom of the box.
      - Pennant and flag, 1910; AC.021.00001 (Box 21)
      - Cream colored cloth with Tufts insignia, undated; AC.021.00002 (Box 21)
      - Pops! Tufts Night banner, 1910; AC.021.00003 (Box 21)
      - Alpha Epsilon Pi purple leather cloth, circa 1940 -- 2007; AC.021.00004 (Box 21)
      - Brown leather Tufts cloth, 1916; AC.021.00005 (Box 21)
      - Brown and blue cap with '32 pin, circa 1932; AC.021.00006 (Box 21)
      - Purple purse, 1915; AC.021.00007 (Box 21)
      - Purple beret, 1915; AC.021.00008 (Box 21)
      - Yellow and black graduation hood, circa 19th -- 20th century; AC.021.00009 (Box 21)
      - Patchwork cloth of Tufts photographs, 1900; AC.021.00010 (Box 21)
      - Class of 1861 cloth, 1900; AC.021.00011 (Box 21)
      - Black and yellow graduation hood, circa 19th -- 20th century; AC.022.00001 (Box 22)
      - Jackson College cardigan, circa 1910 -- 1970; AC.022.00002 (Box 22)
      - Cloth with Tufts embroidery, circa 1875 -- 1935; AC.022.00003 (Box 22)
      - Felt cloth with "1920" sewed on, circa 1920; AC.022.00004 (Box 22)
    - Hat labelled "Ritschy", circa 1911; AC.039.00001 (Box 39)
    - Reunion hat, class of 1910, circa 1935 -- 1960; AC.051.00001 (Box 51)
    - Freshman beanie, circa 1854 -- 1967; AC.051.00002 (Box 51)
- Coins, circa 335 BCE -- 1995 CE; AC.002.000002
  No order has been immposed on this series.
  This series contains coins from Europe, Asia, Africa, and the Americas dating circa 338 BCE -- 1995.
  - Coins, circa 335 BCE -- 1961 CE; AC.010 (Box 10)
    This box contains Roman, Greek and Saxon coins dating circa 335 BCE -- 1000 CE; European coins dating circa 1000 -- 1900 CE; and European, Asian, and African coins dating circa 1900 – 1961.
  - A.B. Fletcher dime and caption, 1923; AC.011.00021 (Box 11)
  - Coins, circa 430 BCE -- 1995 CE; AC.024 (Box 24)
    This box contains Roman, Greek, and Saxon coins dating circa 430 BCE -- 628 CE; European coins dating circa 979 -- 1324; and European, Asian, and South American coins dating circa 1547 -- 1995.
  - Coins, circa 338 BCE -- 1964 CE; AC.049 (Box Shared 12)
    This box contains Roman and Byzantine coins dating circa 338 BCE – 1203 CE; European coins dating circa 1289 – 1964; American coins dating circa 1850s; a few Mexican and Lebanese coins from dating circa 1950s; a Tufts commemorative coin, circa 1913; and a few unidentified coins.
- Cuneiform, scarabs, memorial slab, and tomb figure, circa 2150 BCE -- 0100 CE; AC.003.000002; 8 Artifact(s)
  This series contains examples of cuneiform writing, scarabs, and a tomb figure of a pharaoh dating from circa 2150 BCE – 1924 BCE, as well as a Roman memorial slab dating circa 0100 CE.
  No order has been imposed on this series.
  - Roman Memorial Slab, circa 0100 CE; AC.014.00001 (Box 14)
    John W. Zarker, Chair of the Classics Department, Tufts University (1971-1989), identified and translated the inscription. He noted that the provenance of the slab is unknown other than a notation on the back of the stone casing reading 'Mavor Collection.' To the best of his knowledge this inscription has not been published. According to John Zarker, the names are not listed in Pauly-Wissowa nor in the usual epigraphical publications or prosopographies. Date is approximate. Full text (abbreviation supplied): [D(is)] M (anibus sacrum) [L(uci)] Herenni Pto lemaei Miles C(lassis) P(raetoria) M(isenensis) (e) III (triere) Lucifero Nat(us) Aegypti Mil(itavit) an(nis) XXV Vix(it) an(nis) XLIV T(itus) Iulius Numisian(us) III (trium) libero(rum) p9ater) her(es) b(ene) m(erenti) f(ecit)> Translation: This monument is sacred to the Gods of the Underworld of [Lucius} Herennius Ptolemaeus, a soldier of the praetorian fleet stationed at Misenum from the trireme Lucifer. Born in Egypt he was a soldier for twenty five years; he lived forty four years. Titus Iulius Numisianus, father of three children, as heir set up this monument for Herennius who well deserved it.
  - Scarabs and tablet cuneiform (Sumerian), circa 2112 -- 2050 BCE; AC.017.00006; 3 Artifact(s) (Box Shared 9)
    1: The Small Tablet:
    Introduction: This tablet is written in Sumerian, a language with no linguistic affiliation to any other language known to us. The script used is called cuneiform. The tablet itself can be dated to the Ur III period (ca. 2112-2004 BCE) of ancient Mesopotamia. It contains no further information for more precise dating, except that it was written in the 3rd month (about May-June) of a certain year. Based on the peculiar name of the month, this tablet may well have come from ancient Umma, a Ur III province approximately 300 km south of Baghdad today. In terms of genre, this tablet is an administrative document of the period, a period from which tens of thousands records like this tablet were preserved and a period that is considered one of the most richly documented era throughout the history of Mesopotamia.
    Transliteration and Translation: Legends: ( )word not written down but implied [ ] broken and unrecognizable signs ? ? signs partly broken, but can be restored with certainty ? signs with uncertain reading ! signs not written in the way as might be expected from the context, probably resulting from the mistake or confusion of the scribe Capital Letters: literal reading of the sign, without really understanding its meaning in context Italicized Letters: Sumerian proper names adopted in English translation
    1. 1 (bán) 5 sìla še lugal 10+5 liters of barley 2. UD? ŠA NI IB DU ? meaning of this line unclear 3. šà-gal-ne-ne as their fodder 4. a-hu-ma-ti Ahumati 5. kaskal-ta ì-im-du-a who will travel 6. šu ba-ti received (them) 7. iti še-kar-?ál Month III (Umma)
    Identified and translated by Xiaoli Ouyang, a Ph.D. student working at the Harvard Semitic Museum, March/April 2006.
    Because the cuneiform cone had never been clearly identified or translated (information was based on what the donor, J. Welch had sent with the items), Susanne Belovari, archivist for reference and collections, asked the Semitic Harvard Museum to look at the cone. This is how Ms. Ouyang came to identify and translate this and all other cuneiform.
    2. The Medium-Sized Tablet: Introduction: This tablet is written in Sumerian and uses the cuneiform script. It dates to the Ur III period, more precisely, to the 8th month (about October-November) of the 8th year of Amar-Sîn, the third king of this dynasty (approx. mid-21st century BCE). Based on the appearance of Abbašaga, an official well-known in Puzriš-Dagan (modern Drehem, south of Baghdad today), this tablet could well have been excavated there. It is an administrative text concerning the withdrawal of domestic animals. Obv. 1. 5 udu 5 sheep 2. 5 máš-gal 5 (male) goats 3. me-dištaran Me'Ištaran ? 4. ?ìr a-na-ti sukkal conveyed by Anati, secretary; 5. lugal-kù-zu maškim Lugal-kuzu is the one who approves; 6. šà mu-DU lugal from the royal delivery; lower edge: ?ud?-25-kam on the 25th day; Rev. 7. ki ab-ba-ša6-ga-ta from Abbašaga ? 8. ba-zi withdrew. 9. blank 10. iti šu-eš5-ša Month VIII 11. mu en eriduki ba-hun AS 8
    Explanation: Me-Ishtaran withdrew 5 sheep and 5 goats, either from a group of animals known as the royal delivery, or as part of his contribution to the royal delivery. They were conveyed by Anati and Lugal-kuzu approved this transaction.
    Because the cuneiform cone had never been clearly identified or translated (information was based on what the donor, J. Welch had sent with the items), Susanne Belovari, archivist for reference and collections, asked the Semitic Harvard Museum to identify and transcribe this and all other cuneiforms.
    3: an Egyptian clay tablet.
  - Clay cone, cuneiform, circa 2150s -- 2110s BCE; AC.039.00006 (Box 39)